by the time of diagnosis diabetic
patients have lost approximately 50% of
their insulin producing pancreatic beta
cells according to autopsy studies this
loss is a slow process that ends with
the individual experiencing full-blown
diabetes I have good news pancreatic
beta cells are not permanently damaged
during the early stages of the disease
and can be restored to normal function
with proper lifestyle and environmental
modifications welcome to True Health
Tuesdays I'm Dr Kenisha Reynolds a
licensed naturopathic functional
medicine physician molecular biologist
and former CSI forensic scientist today
we're going to discuss simple and
effective lifestyle modifications that
can improve blood sugar first let's
start out with exercise because exercise
is incredibly important for our
health a sedentary lifestyle can
contribute to insulin resistance and
lead to type 2 diabetes movement
improves blood sugar metabolism by
improving insulin receptor sensitivity
just 30 minutes of postp parand brisk
walking improves the glycemic response
after meals three 15minute periods after
meals is significantly more effective
than 45 minutes of sustained morning or
afternoon walking and lowering post
dinner glucose if you're not used to
exercise start slow start slow start
small you can do it start with 15 minute
brisk walk-in sessions twice a day five
days a week and if you're one of those
people who sit all day I encourage you
to break up your sedentary life
lifestyle with small bouts of movement
set a reminder to get up and walk for 5
minutes every 30 minutes of sitting just
5 minutes break up your prolonged
sitting moderate intensity walking is
feasible and can be easily performed
without the need of fancy equipment or
supervision so it's very easy to get
moving and it's almost a shame that many
people sit all day it's so simple to to
do get up and move for 5 minutes every
30 minutes exercise not only improves
our blood sugar metabolism but it also
helps us with weight management being
overweight or obese greatly increases
your risk for type 2 diabetes the more
excess weight you have the more
resistant your muscle and other cells
are to insulin more than 90% of people
with type 2 diabetes are overweight or
affected by some degree of
obesity exercise acutely burns fat and
endurance training increases the
capacity to burn fat unhealthy fat from
the diet or maybe the fat that you wear
around the waistline gums up insulin
receptors interfering with glucose entry
into the cell sugar accumulates in the
bloodstream and causes damage to our
blood vessels our eyes our kidneys and
our nerve tissue so exercise can
definitely help to improve BMI and
reduce the risk for type 2 diabetes
however a better predictor of type 2
diabetes is the waste to hip ratio a
normal waste to hip ratio for men is
less than
0.95 and for women less than 8 those
would a waste hip ratio of one or
greater have an increased risk for type
diabetes do you ever wonder when's the
best time of day to exercise if you have
type 2 diabetes in a study published in
the Journal of Diabetes Care researchers
determined that those who engaged in
moderate to vigorous physical activity
in the afternoon had the greatest
reduction in blood glucose levels after
one year but if you can't work out in
the afternoon that's totally fine
generally exercising at any time of the
day can help lower blood sugar levels by
increasing insulin sensitivity and
facilitating glucose uptake in the cells
insulin sensitivity increases for at
least 16 hours post exercise so folks
you have to get moving because exercise
is incredibly important for balancing
blood sugar and remember if you're not
used to exercising always set small
goals and Achieve those small goals get
moving every day start out small with
simple short bouts of movement that can
be incredibly
useful our next topic that's really
really critical for stabilizing blood
sugar is sleep sleep is foundation to
our health and our physiology we have to
sleep sleep is controlled by our
circadium clock the circadium rhythm is
the body's internal 24-hour clock that's
naturally aligned with the cycle of day
and night sleep deprivation affects
circadian rhythm which is associated
with type 2
diabetes in fact a single night of sleep
restriction up to 4 hours induces
insulin resistance that's right when
you're not sleeping folks this can
increase your risk for insulin
resistance you have to sleep sleep is
important for our metabolism what you
want to do to improve your sleep hygiene
is most importantly avoid looking at
bright screens 2 to 3 hours before bed
if you work a night shift or use a lot
of electronic devices at night consider
wearing blue blocking glasses or
installing an app on your cell your
device or your computer that filters the
blue green wavelengths at
night you might consider also using
lighting that reflects the sunset colors
such as red orange and yellow these are
fantastic colors that mimic Sunset and
wouldn't so much disrupt your circadian
clock next avoid large meals too close
to bedtime not only does it impact our
gut and our microbiome but it also
affects our circadian rhythm not only
large meals but late night snacking is
also included in that so try to avoid
these practices so that you can improve
your quality of sleep and duration of
sleep sleep with a cooler room ambient
room temperatures should be between 60°
fah to 68 degrees Fahrenheit according
to the sleep Foundation One study found
that sleeping in a cool room set to 66°
can help prevent the onset of metabolic
diseases such as diabetes stop drinking
caffeine 8 hours before bedtime even at
6 hours caffeine can reduce sleep by
more than 1 hour so no caffeinated
beverages folks get early morning light
exposure genes that help control
circadium rhythms are more active in
natural light getting exposure to
sunlight in the morning can help improve
sleep it resets our internal clock
exposure to natural daylight is
beneficial to metabolism and can help
treat and prevent type 2 diabetes and
other cardi metabolic diseases work in
an office with almost no exposure to
natural light will have an impact on
metabolism and your risk or control of
type 2 diabetes so try to get as much
natural light exposure as you can to
help improve your blood sugar
metabolism next environmental toxicants
we're exposed to many of them evidence
indicates that environmental toxicants
chemicals or substances increase the
risk for type 2 diabetes any toxic
chemical that directly injure or cause
dysfunction to pancreatic beta cells is
a diaben diaben have been implicated in
metabolic diseases such as obesity
non-alcoholic fatty liver disease and
diabetes common diabet that you should
be aware of that have been disruptors of
insulin producing cells include things
like bisphenol a or BPA commonly used in
Plastics arsenic a heavy metal Phat and
past chemicals and other chemicals that
are found in pesticides BPA and other
chemicals can either directly act on
pancreatic cells promote oxidative
stress and impair insulin and glucagon
secretion or act on atpo cells muscles
and liver cells to impair function and
trigger an insulin resistant State take
steps to reduce your toxin exposure by
using clean products and avoiding
Plastics I challenge you to go one week
without using Plastics always check your
products using an app that you can
download to your phone called think
dirty it's very powerful is very useful
and being able to check what kind of
products that you're using and if
they're safe if you can't eat it don't
put it on your skin and our very last
topic that I like to discuss that's
plays a role in improving our metabolism
and glucose metabolism at that Balan in
our blood sugar is the
microbiome the digestive tract is home
to many Resident bacteria in the colon
we have anywhere between 300 to a
thousand different bacterial species we
have the ability to influence the gut
microbiota to increase healthy bacteria
in a gut the microbiome is potentially
the most important developments over the
past decade or two it's an incredibly
exciting and emerging field that has
evolved and very blessed to utilize Next
Generation sequencing technology to
really investigate the microbiome in my
years of experience working as a
laboratory scientist and using Advanced
Technologies from thermal Fisher and
apply bios systems have utilized Next
Generation sequence and Technology to
really get an in-depth understanding of
the microbiome and its role in health
we've been able to examine these
microbial systems and their influence on
the host through modulating the immune
system and maintaining intestinal and
bloodb brain Integrity thousands of
Publications over the past decade have
revealed that the trons of bacteria in
the gut could have profound effects on
human health and diseases such as
inflammatory bowel disease disas and
conditions that affect the brain and
conditions that affect metabolism
research is now exploring ways to
manipulate the microbiome to develop new
therapeutic for a variety of diseases
such as irritable bowel disease and
allergic airway disease the gut
microbiome modulates our metabolism
immune GI and CNS central nervous system
physiology it has protective functions
being able to out compete heat pathogens
it regulates gene expression a in
digestion and absorption participates in
the production of vitamins and other
precursor molecules that have a very
important role in our health when a
microbiome is disrupted we call it
disbiosis disbiosis has been implicated
in many disease States including
metabolic diseases such as type 2
diabetes bacterial imbalances can lead
to an overabundance of bacteria that
produce endotoxins higher levels of
endotoxins lead to insulin resistance
endotoxins bind to insulin receptors
promoting insulin resistance causing
sugar to accumulate in the bloodstream
and excessive sugar in the blood not
only is inflammatory to our cells but it
can also store us fat leading to weight
gain utilizing a microbiome as a target
for metabolic diseases have been well
elucidated
administration of microbial species
selective for their known beneficial
role in metabolism is a promising new
tool that augments traditional dietary
measures for improving glucose levels in
type two diabetes the gut microbiome
released short chain fatty acids and
berate is one of those short chain fatty
acids that's able to influence blood
sugar levels by binding to a receptor
called G protein the gut microbiome
produces small molecules such as short
chain fatty acids and butyrate is one of
those short chain fatty acids that's
able to influence glucose metabolism by
binding to G protein coupled receptors
to stimulate glp1 release glp1 is a
hormone known to decrease post glucose
meal spikes and A1C pendulum
Therapeutics is an evidence-based
microbiome company that demonstrates
clinical improvements in A1C and blood
glucose spikes in people with type 2
diabetes pendelum glucose control is the
first multistrain medical probiotic
clinically shown and specifically
designed for the management of type 2
diabetes this probiotic contains five
different strains of important bacteria
that play a role in modulating
metabolism one in famous bacteria that's
often lost in a lot of people with
metabolic dysfunction or metabolic
diseases is acromania and acromania
levels tend to be low in patients with
type 2 diabetes and it plays a very
important role in maintaining the
intestinal barrier function as well so
acromania is one one of those key
microbes that are inside this
multistrain
probiotic if you're not sure what your
microbiome looks like and you have type
two diabetes consider targeting your
microbiome and really looking into your
gut health as a way to improving your
blood sugar levels so in
summary make sure to get moving start
small set small goals achieve those
small goals
break up prolong sitting every 30
minutes of sitting get up and walk 5
minutes make sure you're
sleeping make sure you're getting
Outdoors getting exposed to Natural
Light making sure that you're practicing
good sleep
hygiene and get a sleep study if you're
not sure if you have sleep apnea because
this also impacts blood sugar so be very
keen on your sleep practices and
evaluate how you can improve your sleep
if you're not
sleeping
and also make sure that you're not
exposing yourself to chemicals you're
checking your products you're making
sure that you're not utilizing products
that could be hormone endocrine
disrupting chemicals interfere with your
insulin
function and lastly take a look at your
gut health thank you so much for joining
me today be sure to click the like And
subscribe and share the information with
your loved ones